A Guide to the The Paul Victorius Evolution Collection,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Cartoons and Illustrations Re Charles Darwin, 1863-1909, 15 items; Photocopies. Originals in Oversize Box W-6. (Box-folder 1:90)
  Figaro. London:Wednesday, February 18, 1874. "Prof. Darwin. This is the ape of form." Broadside for "Krao. The Missing Link." on [1887 March 23.] Unidentified. [1738]. Two blurbs on "a strange creature taken in Guinea." Unidentified. [1762]. On finding a strange animal like a human. Unidentified. 1872 June 8. "Natural Selection." Illustrated Times. "No. 10. -The Origin of Garotte." Illustrated Times. "No. 9. -Catch himself asleep." The Comic News. 1863 December 5. "Are We Not All Brothers?" The Daily Telegraph. Thursday, February 11, 1909. "Centenary of Charles Darwin. Gospel of Evolution." Pictorial World. 1874 June 6. "Mr. Darwin." Illustrated Times. 1868 April 4. "Monkey Types in Zoological Gardens, Cologne." The Illustrated London News. 1887 December 10. "The Late Mr. Darwin." Illustrated Times. 1863 June 13. "No. 7. -Piggish." Funny Folks. 1875 February 6. "A 'Caudal' Lecture." Fun. 1872 November 16. "That Troubles our Monkey Again." Fun. 1871 July 22. "A Little Lecture by Professor D-N on the Development of the Horse." Moonshine. 1881 October 29. "Days with Celebrities."
- Caricature of Charles Darwin from Vanity Fair, title "Natural Selection," 1871 September 30, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:91)
- Newspaper Clippings Re Charles Darwin, 1873-1909, 17 items. Photocopies. Originals in Oversize Box W-6. One original clipping glued to notes about David Hume. (Box-folder 1:92)
  The Figaro. London: Wednesday, February 18, 1874. "Man Not Monkey." The Graphic. 1880 September 4. The Times Weekly Edition. 1882 April 23. "Charles Robert Darwin's Obituary." The Times Weekly Edition. 1882 April 28. "The Death of Mr. Darwin." The Times Weekly Edition. 1882 September 29. "Professor Haeckel on Darwin." The Times Weekly Edition. 1882 April 28. "The Funeral of Mr. Darwin." The Leeds Mercury [ ]. 1887 November 27. "Darwin and His Books," and "Carnations in Winter." Pall Mall Budget. 1888 February 9. "The Gospel According to Darwin -II." Pall Mall Budget. 1888 November 1. "Darwin's Schools and Schoolmasters." Daily Mail. London: Wednesday, September 2, 1908. "A Darwin Jubilee." The Daily News. Friday, February 12, 1909. "Two Notable Centenaries." Unidentified. 1909 February 12. "Charles Darwin" by Alfred Russel Wallace. The Daily Chronicle. 1909 June 24, "Darwin's Kentish Home." Unidentified. 1909. "Two Leaders of Men. Centenary Births of Darwin and Lincoln." Unidentified. n.d. "'Mr. Darwin's Descent of Man.'" [Pall Mall] Budget. n.d. "The Gospel According to Darwin.-I." Unidentified. n.d. Photographs of Downe, Beckingham, Kent, and "The Fate of Darwin's Apparatus."
- Ticket for Charles Darwin's funeral, 1882 April 26, D; with wax seal. (Box-folder 1:93)
- Program for Charles Darwin's funeral, 1882 April 26, D. (Box-folder 1:94)
- Newspaper Clipping on Charles Lyell, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:95)
- Elston Hall, where Erasmus Darwin was born, ante 1754, Print (electro-static copy), 1 item. (Box-folder 1:96)
- "Doctor's Plate" of Erasmus Darwin, 1771, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:97)
  Mounted on acidic card. Verso of card contains notes on Erasmus Darwin along with a facsimile of his signature in 1783.
- Sketch of Dr. James Hutton, 1787, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:98)
- "Erasmus Darwin, author of The Loves of the Plants," 1803 February 1, 1 item. Oversize Box V-13 (Box-folder 1:99)
  "Rawlinson pinx. ad viv. R. Courbould del."
- Engraving of Erasmus Darwin, painted by Rawlinson, engraved by Haughton, 1807 January 1., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:100)
- Engraving of Erasmus Darwin, 1828 July 1, 1item. (Box-folder 1:101)
- Robert Waring Darwin, 1839 February 1, 1 engraving. Oversize Box V-13 (Box-folder 1:102)
  "Painted by James Fardon Shrewsbury. Engraved by Thomas Lupton."
- Lithograph of Charles Darwin by S.H. Maguire, 1849, 1 item. Oversize Box V-13. (Box-folder 1:103)
  Signed by Darwin.
- Lithograph of Charles Lyell by S.H. Maguire, 1849, 1 item. Oversize Box V-13. (Box-folder 1:104)
- Photograph of Charles Darwin, 1869, Photograph, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:105)
- Photographs of Charles Darwin, by Julia Margaret [Cameron?], 1868, 2 items. Oversize Box V-13 (Box-folder 1:106)
  Both signed by C.D., one inscribed "this photograph very much better than any other which has been taken of me."
- Photograph of Jos[eph] D[alton]Hooker, President of the R[oyal] S[ociety], Director of Royal Gardens, Kew, 1878, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:107)
- Photograph of Mrs. Charles Darwin 1896 July, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:108)
- Engravings, some hand colored, of fossils for publication, n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 1:109)
- Print of Breadsall Priory, where Erasmus Darwin died, n.d., 1 item; electrostatic copy. (Box-folder 1:110)
- H.M.S. Beagle, "Terra del Fuego," by [Conrad Martens], n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:111)
  Glued to backing.
- H.M.S. Beagle, "Mount Sarmiento in Terra del Fuego," by [Conrad Martens], n.d., 1 item; with photograph. (Box-folder 1:112)
  Watercolor reproduced in Moorhead's Darwin and the Beagle (Penguin 1971).
- Photograph of Charles Darwin, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:113)
- Engraving of Charles Darwin, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:114)
- Statue of Charles Darwin, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:115)
- Photograph of Bust of Charles Darwin made by Horace Montford, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:116)
- Print of [Erasmus Darwin], n.d., 1 item; electrostatic copy. (Box-folder 1:117)
- Bookplate of William Erasmus Darwin, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:118)
- Photograph of Thomas Henry Huxley, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:119)
  Printed for subscribers to Appleton's Scientific Library.
- Photograph of Thomas Henry Huxley, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:120)
- Photograph of Herbert Spencer, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:121)
- Photograph of John Tyndall, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:122)
- Portraits, n.d., 5 items. Oversize Box V-13. (Box-folder 1:123)
  Engraving of Robert Chambers, by D.J. Pound, from a photograph by Mayell n.d. Watercolor of Charles Darwin and Thomas Henry Huxley, n.d. Watercolor of Thomas Henry Huxley, n.d.[Herbert Spencer?], n.d. Engraving of Charles Darwin by Rajonag, n.d. Inscribed "with kind regards to Prescott Hewett, Esq. From W.W. O[?]"